hey everyone welcome back to the store
score automation playlist and today I am
going to talk about another interesting
topic uh which our feature which is
available in Tosca
now many a times uh we need to encode or
decode some text or some value in our
test automation suit right so something
like the passwords the usernames or the
environment details the DB password or
the username right so there are many
things which uh you probably need to
encode or decode as part of your
security concerns around the whole test
automation suit or even maybe you need
to encode or decode some test data right
so in this kind of cases you can use one
of the string operations uh which is
available in Tosca
to encode and decode any particular text
so let me show you how you can do this
in Tosca
so for this purpose I'm going to use
this particular page okay and it has got
some username and password right
and to login we need this username and
password and what I'm going to do is I'm
going to encode this username and encode
this password and then I'm going to
decode it okay
so first of all what I have done I have
stored this a username and password
right here okay
and it is stored in the configuration
parameters for this particular test case
so first of all I'm going to create a
test step and I'm going to use the t-box
set buffer
okay so this will set a buffer value for
the encoded values okay and I'm going to
name this to encode underscore username
and in this value we need to now write
the expression which can basically
encode a particular string which is in
our case is a username okay
so let me explain you what I have done
here so we are using this base 64
expression okay which basically allows
us to encode that is also at the end of
this expression there is a parameter
called encode and what we want to encode
so that's our text which is a
configuration parameter in terms of the
username okay so using this it is going
to encode it in the base64 format okay
um and the same we can do for password
uh what I need to do is just copy this
or I can also type it but to just make
it more faster I'll just copy it and
change it to password
okay
so this is basically going to encode our
username and password so let's quickly
run this and see if it is working or not
okay so the test has passed and now in
the log info you will be able to see the
encoded value of this username okay so
this is the encoded value it's some
random string which has been generated
to basically mask the particular
username okay so when this data travels
over or when it is used for test
automation you will be seeing this
encoded username
and then there is also encoded password
so you don't need to actually show your
actual password you can use this encoded
password right
um now in order to use it in a
particular test right we need the actual
values otherwise if I go ahead and use
it in this particular login form it is
probably going to fail right
so uh for that again I can add the same
test step which is t-box set buffer
okay and then I'm going to name this
buffer as decode user name
and
I will again have another one for decode
password
okay and
the expression okay so it will be pretty
much similar let me show you how you can
write this so you write base64 and then
you start the square brackets and under
this we are not going to use the
configuration parameter because we need
to pass a string which is already
encoded okay so we have to use this
particular buffer so we'll use encode
underscore username
and then we need to pass the parameter
decode here so that it will be decoded
okay
so that's what we have to do again for
password we have to do the same
and
password okay
uh so that's that's the thing that you
need to do let's run this quickly to
check whether it is working or not
okay so it failed let's check what's
wrong here
okay
um so instead of the buffer I used a
text okay so which is not a encoded text
so obviously that will fail so let me
correct this uh be unders so we'll start
with the buffer which is B and then
square brackets and we will use the
encode username here
okay and then this
the same we will do for password
okay so let's try one more time this
time it should pass
okay so this is now going to decode our
actual encoded username and password and
it's going to return us the same value
which we stored in the configuration
parameter
okay
uh maybe I did not change this sorry
about that let me change it to password
but it should work still the same right
okay so it has decoded the username and
password and we have seen how it encodes
the username and password now you will
ask me uh why do we need to do this
right so this is not uh the best
possible example I could give you but I
wanted to show you how you can encode
and decode strings in Tosca this could
be useful in some scenarios
in real time scenario you would not be
encoding and decoding the same strings
in the same test probably you should
have some encoded text okay which is
maybe a buffer or some other value
which has been provided to you and then
you are going to use that in the test so
at that time you can maybe use the
decode function right and sometimes
maybe
um after you uh get some values from the
application right maybe you are testing
an application and the application has
returned you some order ID or some
um some customer information right which
you need to encode and store it so that
time you can use the encode function
okay so don't take this example as
literally what you need to do you need
to apply this functions at different
places okay so you need to apply and
code where you want to encode a
particular string and you need to apply
the code when you want to decode a
particular string okay so this I find it
a very useful function because we need
this at some places during test
automation
so that's all for this particular video
I hope you liked it and you learned
something new today if you have any
questions please leave them in the
comment section if you want to watch
more similar videos please do subscribe
to our Channel
and until we meet again
keep learning Tosca and keep watching
our Channel